In theoretical physics, especially in the
theory of relativity and quantum mechanics,
we will regularly encounter symmetric and
antisymmetric tensors.
A symmetric tensor t_ remains the same
if we swap its indices.
Specifically, swapping the indices of the
second-level tensor as a matrix means that
the matrix remains the same if we transpose
it, in other words if we mirror the rows and
columns on the diagonal.
This symmetry property of tensors is very
useful and simplifies calculations in computer
physics enormously.
Moreover, this property is crucial in quantum
mechanics, because symmetric matrices have
real eigenvalues.
They therefore represent physical quantities
(we call them observables) that we can measure
in an experiment.
So if you have a symmetric tensor in front
of you, as a theoretical physicist you should
immediately get a dopamine kick.
The Kronecker delta, for example, is an example
of a simple symmetric tensor.
We have considered a second-order tensor.
What if the tensor is of a HIGHER order?
What about its symmetry property THEN?
For example, if the tensor has four indices
and it remains EQUAL when we swap the first
two indices, then we are talking about a symmetric
tensor in the indices m and k.
However, we will also encounter tensors that
are antisymmetric.
An antisymmetric tensor changes sign when
we swap its indices.
If the antisymmetric tensor is represented
as a matrix, then it is equal to its negative
transpose.
Unfortunately, most tensors are neither symmetric
nor antisymmetric.
But the great thing is: Mathematically, we
can split every tensor T into a symmetric
and an antisymmetric part: T is equal to S
plus A.
Let's take a look at how we practically split
a general second-level tensor T into its two
parts.
The symmetric part S of the tensor T is "One
and a half times t_ plus t_.
In the second term, we have swapped the two
indices.
Then we added the two tensors together.
The factor of one and a half is important
because we have counted the tensor twice here.
The antisymmetric part A of the tensor T is
"One and a half times t_, minus t_.
Here we have swapped the two indices, which
gives the swapped tensor a minus sign.
The factor of one and a half must not be missing
here either.
We then add the symmetric and antisymmetric
parts together to obtain the total tensor.
We are done.
The first summand is the symmetric part of
the tensor t_ and the second summand is
the antisymmetric part.